<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short narrative by way of vindication of the late honourable Marquesse of Montrosse, his last designe, impartially setting forth the true grounds which moved him to undertake that second imployment, together with the most probable causes of his miscarriage therein.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B43978</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">690988687</idno>
  <idno type="VID">211694</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240870000</idno>
  
            <idno type="OCLC"> 690988687</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 690988687</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3607C</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B43978)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 211694)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2984:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short narrative by way of vindication of the late honourable Marquesse of Montrosse, his last designe, impartially setting forth the true grounds which moved him to undertake that second imployment, together with the most probable causes of his miscarriage therein.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>165-?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: University of Toronto. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Montrose, James Graham, --  Marquis of, 1612-1650 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Scotland --  History --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:211694:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:211694:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:211694:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A short Narrative by way of Vindication of the late Honourable Marquesse of</hi> Montrosse, <hi>his last Designe, impartially set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth the true grounds which moved him to undertake that second imployment, together with the most probable causes of his miscarriage therein.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO unlock the secret Riddles of Divine Providence, or make discovery of the strange and unparalleld Changes this Age hath brought forth, is a Worke fitter for an OEDIPUS then my selfe; yet for satisfaction of well affected mindes, who have not had the benefit and opportunity to be throughly informed of each particular truth, &amp; rectifying the misguided judgements of such as give credit to all vulgar Reports without any just examination; as also the clearing of many mistakes that somewhat sowrely reflect upon persons not rightly concerned, and as Justice and Equity requires, setting the saddle upon the right horse: Have I adventured to set Pen to Paper, and make the world acquainted with such observations of the truth of things, as in my travells abroad (not without some paines, and cost, and danger too) I have acquired touching the late Lord Marquesse of MON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TROSSE, his last Engagement and miscarriage therein.</p>
            <p>That cursed faction, which was first hatched in Scotland, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards nursed and brought up in England, having attained its fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l growth, and come to that ripenesse of Rebellion, as to destroy that peerelesse Prince CHARLES the First, of blessed Memory: The un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy newes of his death, together with those Acts of the English State (as they called themselves) for Abolition of Monarchy, and disinherisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Heire apparent to that Crowne and Kingdome (designed of purpose utterly to extirpate the Royal Family, Root and Branch) soone arrived at the Hague, where the Prince of Wales then resided, and filled all mens mindes with astonishment at the horrour of the fact: A dumbe silence for a good while possessed their soules, griefe and amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment stupified their understandings, and so many perplexities pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed their Reason, that for the present they knew not which way to turne, what advice or course to take to expedite themselves out of that deplorate condition, till time (the cure of mighty cares) had let them
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:211694:3"/> breath out their mournfull sorrowes, and after some few weekes, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peld those clouds of griefe by intervention of sundry Agents from For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine Princes, sent to the now newly proclaimed King of Scotland, partly to condole his Fathers death, partly to comfort and cheere up his drooping spirits, with hopes, if not promises of assistance. And that Forrainers might not outstrip his Native Subjects, obliged by more strict ties of Loyalty and Religion, divers of the Nobility and Gentry (His Majesties exiled Subjects) from all parts flocked to the Court, and as their Allegiance bound them, made tender of their service to their yong King: Brave Loyall soules, who had lost all the estates they had in defence of (their Prince) the Father, his just Cause, Crowne and Dignity, were now ready, and offered themselves to venture all that was left, their lives, in restoring (their Prince likewise) his Son, to his just Rights and Inheritance. To compleat this Loyal Tribe, came that Renowned Scot, the Marquesse of MONTROSSE, one famous all the world over, not more for his Eminent Loyalty, knowne Prudence and integrity▪ then for his Valour and skill in Military Affaires, manifested in those signall Victories obtained not long since over the Rebels in Scotland.</p>
            <p>This comfortable appearance soone cleared up the sad face of the Court, and gave life and warmth to their stupified spirits, so as in time they begin to bethinke themselves of the best prudentiall meanes, how to put the yong King into a condition to act for the recovery of his just Rights and Inheritance: And shortly after the Marquesse of MON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TROSSE his comming thither, a Councell was called, wherein his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties most faithfull servants humbly represented unto him, his low, and seemingly deplorate condition, through the power and prevalency of his utter enemies in all or the most part of his Dominions; adding also some pressing Arguments to sharpen him speedily to act some thing for revenge of his Fathers death, whilst his wounds bled a fresh, and the memory of that horrid fact had yet an impression on the hearts of his bleeding Subjects. His Majesty returned them thankes for their pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent advice, and commanded them to consider of some effectuall expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to that purpose, promising withall he would be guided onely by the conduct of their Counsels, who had approved themselves so faithful and loyal to his deceased Father.</p>
            <p>Within few dayes after the Councell met againe, and then by way of expedient they offered these two Proposalls to his Majesties choice;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:211694:3"/> either to send his Embassadours abroad to all Christian Princes for sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies both of men and mony, that an Army might be speedily sent into the North of Scotland to ayd his Loyal Subjects there, who were then risen up in Armes for him, and would receive and proclaime him King without any conditions or limitation: Or else to yield himselfe over to the unreasonable Demands the Scotch Parliament were now about to send him; and so cast himselfe wholly upon that perfidious party in Scotland, who JUDAS like, had sold their Lord and Master, (nay worse then JUDAS, sold their Prince that came to them for protection, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily, if not upon assurance of safety; and to their eternall infamy be it spoken, never repented of it, as JUDAS did, nor brought back the mony, which was the price of their Prince) into the hands of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish, and so were become Accessaries, if not Principalls in their Kings murther: And who by the same Artifice and Legerdemaine, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they had destroyed the Father, sought now to intrap the Son, by proclaiming him King with provisoes, as if he should not enjoy the Kingdome by any naturall Right of Succession and Heirship; but by E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, and mutuall compact between him and his people: For thus to proclaime him King, and by a limitation to deny him the exercise of his Regall Power, is in effect to depose him before he came to the Crown; deposing being nothing else but excluding of Kings from the exercise of that power, which of Right belongs to them.</p>
            <p>The Debate upon these Proposalls was hotly disputed by his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Councell, for those who were truely loyal upon honest and legall Principles, were of opinion the safe way was for his Majesty to enter the North of Scotland with a Forraine force; but such as were loyal onely upon private interest, favouring the sacrilegious ends of the Presbyter, and fearing his Majesties Power if brought in by the sword; were of opinion, his Majesties safest way would be to yield himselfe up to the Parliament of Scotland, who sate there upon the Presbyterian score; for this would be a meanes to sweeten the English Presbyter into a compliance, and taking part with his Majesty, being thus put in hope not only of obtaining pardon, and to be secured from the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they had deserved for their Rebellion against CHARLES the First, but also might catch the Fish which they had so long angled for, the Bishops, and Deane, and Chapters Lands. In conclusion the honest loyal party carryed it by a plurality of Votes; yet before these Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sells could ripen, and they have time to pitch upon a Generall for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:211694:4"/> of those Forraine Forces into the North of Scotland; the Scotch Commissioners arrived in May, 1648. and accordingly as had been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly represented to the King, their Propositions and Deportment was unreasonable and insolent, suitable to the heighth and pride of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian faction; insomuch that that Treaty brake off unluckily with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out satisfaction to either part.</p>
            <p>Neverthelesse his Majesty upon mature deliberation, and by advice of his Councell gave the Marquesse of MONTROSSE a Commission to be his Generall, and to levy and conduct such Forraine Forces as Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian Princes would supply him withall for his assistance; and to land them either in England or Scotland, as might tend most to the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of his Majesties service, and as the necessity and urgency of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Affaires should require. And in like manner to GEORGE MON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RO a Commission was granted by his Majesty to be his Major General, and to levy 4. or 5000. Irish foot to be forthwith in readinesse for the furthering the Marquesse of MONTROSSE his Designe.</p>
            <p>But such is the mischiefe of divided Counsels; no sooner had the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quesse of MONTROSSE taken his leave of His Majesty, but his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries (that favoured the contrary opinion) both Scots and English, who had acted in the rebellion against his Father, do endeavour by all means possible to perswade with His Majesty for recalling the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quesse his Commission: And most cleare it is, this they did partly out of envy at the worth and integrity of the man, partly out of feare his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign should take effect, and so His Majesty become an absolute Monarch, and invested with just power to call them to an account for their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer rebellion. Those of the Scotch Nation, that thus sought to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse MONTROSSE, were Duke HAMILTON, the Earls of CALEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER, and Lauderdale: Of the English, MASSY, GRAVES, Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man BUNCH, and others of the secluded Members. But when they found His Majesty immoveable, His Royall brest impenetrable, by all the force of their subtle perswasions; then they betake themselves to their old tricks, under hand to supplant this Honourable designe, by sending secretly into Scotland some fit instruments, upon specious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, to prevaile with the Loyall party there to lay down Arms, and accept of conditions proffered; by their pollitick alienating the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Prince of ORENGE, the Marquesse of Brandenburg, Count EMDEN, from my Lord of MONTROSSE, and winning them cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly to refuse the affording him assistance either of men or money:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:211694:4"/> In like manner, they privately dispatch Agents abroad to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and divers other Princes of Germany, to the King of Denmark, and the Queen of Sweden, effectually to rancounter his designe: And when they found their sly insinuations, could operate little on those Princes affections, to take them off from MONTROSSE; there Mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like they wrought under ground, and suborn'd the most powerfull In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments of the Court against him.</p>
            <p>The Queen of Sweden (to Her eternall Honour be it spoken) was constant to Her promises, and furnish'd him readily out of Her Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zines, with Armes and Ammunition; but here Chancellor OXEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STERNE, no small friend to, and favourer of the Scots Rebellion, sought by all means possible to crosse those supplies, and hinder him from obtaining either men or money. In Denmark the King was much taken with MONTROSSE, approv'd his designe, and most wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to further it in what he was able; but the Hoff-Master, and sundry others of his Councel, had been privately tamper'd withall, and brought off by these subtle Incendiaries to stand in opposition with the King in whatever he endeavour'd to accommodate the Marquesse of MON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TROSSE his designe: nor was it needfull to solicite the Queens Court at Paris for the furthering their desires in the crossing of this enterprize; the Lord GERMAN and his Faction there having long since expressed spleen enough and animosities sufficient to let all the world take noticc, they were declar'd Enemies to MONTRNSSE, and his underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings.</p>
            <p>Thus craftily behind the curtaine, the Presbyterian party, utter Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the Marquesse of MONTROSSE, acted abroad in all the Courts of Christendome; nor are they asleep or idle at home, as appears by their secret workings with the Scotch Parliament and Committee of Estates, who now were framing a dismall Declaration against their King, which did amount to his deposing, as I said before; in declaring him unfit for the exercise of his Regall power, as having yet suck'd in no other principles, save Praerogative, and Tyranny; bred up under Bishops and Ceremonies, which the Scotch Aire seems to have a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Antipathy unto; one that inwardly hated the Covenant, and would never take otherwise than as a snare to take them therein; one whom they themselves saw so averse from hearkening to any sound Counsell and Advice, that he suffred himself to be seduc'd, by evill Councellors, even to an invasion of their Countrey: I say, notwithstanding the Scots
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:211694:5"/> were setting out this pestilent Declaration against their King, yet were they so effectually wrought with by some crafty Agents, upon assurance His Majesty should be forc'd to disclaime MONTROSSE and his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize, and cast himselfe wholely upon the Scotch Parliament, that a second Treaty is desired from His Majesty, and GEORGE WINDRAM sent a dangerous Winters journey to Jersey upon this message; which by the earnest and dayly solicitation of the Queen his Mother, seconded by the secret perswasions of a Court Faction that favourd it, was yielded unto; and the place appointed for meeting was Breda; the time design'd for that Treaty to begin, March 15. 1649.</p>
            <p>To this I might adde, besides the malice and underhand working of his Adversaries, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here concur'd to the defeating of MONTROSSE his designe, the unhappy disasters which at that conjuncture of time befell the Noble Marquesse of ORMOND in Ireland▪ together with the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiousnesse and treachery of Sir JOHN COCKRAM, who being the Kings Agent abroad, had taken up of the Scots Merchants divers consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable sums of money, by the leave and appointment of the King of Poland, for the promoting my Lord of MONTROSSE his designe, as also for the same purpose great quantities of Corne from the Duke of Courdtland: All which provided and lent for the publique use, he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily misimployed and put into his private pocket</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding these many misfortunes, and hindrances, through indefatigable industry this prudent Marquesse of MONTROSSE in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to his designe, levied, and listed about fourscore Volunteers, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in Holland, all of his owne, whom he speedily accommodated and dispatch'd into the Isle of Orkney, under the conduct of the then Earle of Kennowl. From Denmark likewise, not without many rubs, he procured sixscore more, who were conducted thither also, under the Command of WILLIAM HAY, now Earle of Kennowl. From Got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenbury in Sweden, he listed between twenty and thirty Officers, old German Souldiers; but because then in those parts the Sea was frozen, himselfe never tyred out with incessant pains and dangers (with two or three Gentlemen more in that cold climate travel'd by land to Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and took shipping there for Orkney, where no sooner was he arriv'd, but (behold the Iliads of Mischiefes and machinations of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies!) those Gallant souls he had sent before, were all in a mutiny, and by the subtle practises of some, so divided into Factions as that they were ready to cut one anothers throats.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:211694:5"/>
            <p> During this disorder, before things could be composed, Mr. MAY is sent from His Majesty, with the Garter, and a Letter besides, peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily commanding my Lord forthwith to advance into Scotland.</p>
            <p>The Garter was received with all thankfulnesse, and honourable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect: the Letter with no small joy, out of more then probable hopes, it might be a means to appease the Mutineers, and win them to a sweet compliance for a speedy and chearfull engagement upon the main Land; To this end the Officers and chiefe Gentlemen were assembled, and His Majesties Letter read; the purport whereof was, That His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty being overcome by the importunity of sundry friends, had yielded once more to treat with the Commissioners from the Scots Parliament, at Bredah, March 15. where, by the blessing of God, His Majesty was resolved to do nothing prejudiciall to the Marquesse or his Followers, by whose faithfull endeavours he had reap'd so great fruit and benefit, as to affright the Scotch Faction to designe a Treaty, and make more moderate Proposals than formerly. Therefore that the Marquesse and his loyall party might not be disheartned with the unexpected newes of a Treaty: He desired and commanded him vigorously to prosecute the advancement of that service he had already undertaken for Scotland.</p>
            <p>The Letter ended, my Lord bespake the company to this effect: By what ye have heard, Gentlemen, ye perceive His Majesties most hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Intentions, in this Treaty, his chief care to be, the good and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of His loyall Subjects: therefore it will become us in duty to shew ready obedience to His Majesties Command, and to do our best endeavours, either to reduce the Rebels of Scotland to a due sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission to His Majesties just power, or at least enforce them to tender more moderate Proposals than ever hitherto came from them. And now that he might be assured of their unanimous &amp; hearty concurrence in this designe, he desired them to empty their brests freely, and give him their sober advice touching the same.</p>
            <p>The first that spake, an ingenious Gentleman, told my Lord, that Letter had been printed in France a month before, and in Holland he had read it in the Dutch Gazets, which made him feare it was contriv'd and published to His Majesties dis-service, and the destruction of his Lordship and his followers: for (sayes he) it is well enough knowne to those in JERSEY, that you are disappoynted of the ayd you expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted both from Ireland and forraign Princes; and that your whole number now in Orkney, are not above two hundred strangers:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:211694:6"/> My Lord, is it imaginable His Majesty, or any rationall man, should command you to invade the Isle of Great Brittaine only with 200. men; especially at this instant, when the insulting Factions of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes are united against you? May it please your Excellence to excuse me, if in obedience to your command, I give you my censure freely, touching this Letter sent by Mr. MAY; that it was pen'd by your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies (not ignorant of your undaunted spirit, in attempting difficult things, even such as without a Miracle, it seems scarce possible to be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected) out of designe to spur you on to your own destruction; and partly to render His Majesty odious to all parties, either for a dissem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler with Scots Parliament, or as if he sought your destruction and your Followers by precipitating you to a visible and unavoydable danger. I beseech you pardon my freedome, and be assur'd, whatever my opinion is, I will never forsake you in your most desperate undertakings.</p>
            <p>My Lords Reply was, both his Charity and Loyalty commanded him to think honourably of His Majesties intentions, and though he had cause enough to suspect the Court-Factions, and some others about the Queen, that were his most deadly Enemies; yet he was well perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and hoped it was not in their power (though never so maliciously bent) to withdraw His Majesties affections from them, who had so readily adventured lives and fortunes for his service; notwithstanding their being unworthily deserted and disappointed of assistance from those whom they reputed to be their best and fast friends; neither is it to be immagined, my present expedition into Scotland, should prove either a desperate or impossible enterprize, for though, as you rightly, the Rebels of both Nations be united against us, yet I am well assured, there are many thousands, both of English and Scotch, that are ready and will joyne with us, if any visible Power appears, as is most cleare to me, by some secret correspondence held with the best of the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Gentry of Scotland; from whom this very day most certaine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence is come, that so soon as ever we have set footing on the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, the Highlanders will rise as one man for our assistance: And then reflect but upon some former undertakings, which by the blessing of God, even beyond humane expectation were successefully accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished; when with 1000. Irishes only, God so prospered the upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of a just cause, as to enable us not only to encounter, but to van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quish the Rebels (trembling through guilt of conscience) in 6. or 7. se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Battells.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:211694:6"/>
            <p> This Speech of the Generalls, spoken with such moderation and confidence, suitable to the Greatnesse of his Minde, roused up the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of those Gentlemen and Officers that heard it, presently to cry out, They would live and dye with him; and farther to give him assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance they would engage with him, where and when he pleased to command them. Whereupon immediately whilst their spirits were yet warme, those 200 Volunteers, together with 1000 Islanders were shipped, who all arrived safely in Cathnes on the 9. of April, 1650. and in that Country a Commission was given to Colonell GRAHAM to raise a Regiment there; but Provisions being exceeding scarce in those parts, my Lord was necessitated to march into Sutherland, and from thence to Rosse, where partly to refresh his men, and partly to gaine intelligence, whether the safest way were to march up into the Hills, or to proceed forwards alongst the Sea coast; he stayed two or three dayes: But his Scouts, whether out of carelesnesse, or falshood, or surpriz'd by the Enemy, (for tis not clearely resolved on) fail'd to bring him intelligence; insomuch that April 25. his whole party was unhappily surprized by the Enemy, as they were on their march to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Innernesse, by Major STRAUGHAN and Lievetenant Collonel HACKET, who with 200. Horse, and 1500. experienced Foot Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers Routed his whole Body (the Islanders throwing downe their Armes at the first Charge) as they were upon a Retreat to a Wood, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no quarter to any man, till Sir John HURRY, with about 20. poor Scotch Nags (which were all the Horse my Lord had) charg'd so gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantly Collonel HACKETS Troope, that they forc'd them to give quarter.</p>
            <p>My Lord perceiving by that unhappy skirmish, his whole designe to be in danger to be lost, betooke himselfe to his feet, and only with six Officers marched about 60 miles back againe, hoping to have met with some of his new levies; but finding himselfe much tyred with that long march, he refreshed himselfe neare the Laird of ASHEN, and sent Major SINCLERE out to try if he could get any intelligence, with a guide to direct him to my Lord REA his Country: But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for feare, or bribery, or treachery, I am not able to judge, that Major most unworthily betrayed him into the hands of his enemies, who came suddainly with about 30 or 40 men, and tooke him in his Quarters on the 28. of April, 1650. Whence how uncivilly and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barously he was carryed by Major Generall HOLBURN, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:211694:7"/> that guarded him to Edenborough, I leave for other Pens to paint forth in due time and proper colours; as also with what af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts and contumelious language they proceeded afterwards to try him; and how insultingly they behaved themselves towards him when he was led to execution; having torne in pieces his Majesties Commission, and as much as in them lay re-murtherd CHARLES the First, and testified to all the world their desires and intentions, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise in him to murther CHARLES the Second: That so both Father and Sonne, Root and Branch, and all the rest of the Royal Stems, might be utterly extirpate.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:211694:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>